<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Applied Collaboration | Brianna C. Heggeseth</title>
    <link>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/tag/applied-collaboration/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://bcheggeseth.github.io/tag/applied-collaboration/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Applied Collaboration</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 Brianna C. Heggeseth </copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/media/icon_hu57cb00c344750d07111e480b68a9d566_369349_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Applied Collaboration</title>
      <link>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/tag/applied-collaboration/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Associations with Early Kidney Injuries</title>
      <link>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/project/kidneyfunction/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/project/kidneyfunction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2021, my PhD advisor, Nicholas Jewell, put me in contact with &lt;a href=&#34;https://iris.ucl.ac.uk/iris/browse/profile?upi=BCAPL88&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr. Ben Caplin&lt;/a&gt; of University College of London and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.renalfellow.org/2019/02/08/my-journey-from-nicaragua-to-london-to-study-ckdu-5-lessons-learned/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr. Marvin Gonzalez-Quiroz&lt;/a&gt; and their larger &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5210224/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;DEGREE study team&lt;/a&gt; to help them study the potential causes of chronic kidney disease of unexplained cause (CKDu) among young, apparently healthy individuals in Nicaragua.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information about the epidemic of CKDu in Central America, see the &lt;a href=&#34;https://laislanetwork.org/type/video/page/2/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Cycle of Death video&lt;/a&gt; created by the team members and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thelancet.com/pdfs/journals/langlo/PIIS2214-109X%2814%2970217-7.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;a Lancet article&lt;/a&gt; on the topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The research team have been collecting longitudinal data on cohorts of young, healthy people in Nicaragua. After a two-year follow up, they &lt;a href=&#34;https://jasn.asnjournals.org/content/29/8/2200.short&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;applied longitudinal growth mixture models (GMM) to detect any associations with declining eGFR patterns&lt;/a&gt;. While this statistical approach worked well for a short follow up, it was not as applicable for detecting the underlying cause with a longer 5-year follow up since individuals may start to decline at any point during the study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In collaboration with nephrologists, epidemiologists, and statisticians, I came up with an alternative methodology (details forthcoming in publication) to detect an early kidney injury, the time at which an individual might switch from healthy kidney function to declining, unhealthy kidney function before being clinically diagnosed as having CKD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Macalester students, Alexander McCreight and Connie (Yixuan) Zhang, worked with me to implement this method to investigate potential exposures with early kidney injury. The first paper using this method is currently in review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With my students, we will compare the potential conclusions from the original GMM methodology with this alternative method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Product&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In Progress&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prenatal PFAS and Early Childhood Growth</title>
      <link>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/project/prenatalpfas/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/project/prenatalpfas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2016, &lt;a href=&#34;https://geiselmed.dartmouth.edu/epidemiology/people/faculty/megan-romano/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr. Megan Romano&lt;/a&gt; of Dartmouth University contacted me regarding my expertise in longitudinal methods for childhood growth. I helped her write a grant proposal and started working as a statistical consulting on this approved grant that seeks to estimate the relationship between prenatal exposure to PFAS and childhood adiposity growth over time. I wrote the analysis plan, implemented it, and we are writing up the conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Product&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In Progress&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mia Collaboration</title>
      <link>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/project/miacollaboration/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/project/miacollaboration/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the Fall of 2019, I start working the the publicly available collection data at &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/artsmia/collection&#34;&gt;https://github.com/artsmia/collection&lt;/a&gt;. I reached out to staff at the Minneapolis Institute of Art and we found that I could help them achieve new goals for analyzing their collection data. With the help of Macalester students, we have provided internal reports of analysis of art object metadata and location history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Products&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Independent Projects&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/connie-zhang-311081194&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Connie Zhang&lt;/a&gt; in Fall 2019-Summer 2020: Visitor Experience and Art Object Tag Creation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/thudang24/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Thu Dang&lt;/a&gt; in Summer 2020: Visualization of Deaccession of Art Objects over time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/jiaying-wu-work/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Jiaying Wu&lt;/a&gt; in Summer 2021: Reflection Tool for Mia Collecting Goals; Presentation to Chief Curator and Mia Staff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Internal Department Reports&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Summary of Accession and Deaccession over Time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Summary of Location Purpose of Art Objects over Time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Summary of Use of Gallery Space&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Diversity of artists in major U.S. museums</title>
      <link>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/project/artistdiversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/project/artistdiversity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In collaboration with a team of applied mathematicians, statisticians, and art historians and curators, I used data science and machine learning tools to estimate the diversity of artists at 18 U.S. art museums. The project goal was to make inferences about artist characteristics to summarize the diversity of a museum’s collection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We performed data collection by web scraping information about the collections at the chosen art museums, designed the sampling method to create a subset of artists to focus on, and created a website that provides access to our final data set as well as graphical summaries for broad access to our results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work has been covered in international news outlets including the San Francisco Chronicle, Smithsonian Magazine, The Guardian (UK), Minnesota Public Radio, and MIT Technology Review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Products&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/url?q=https%3A%2F%2Fjournals.plos.org%2Fplosone%2Farticle%3Fid%3D10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0212852&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;sntz=1&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNHXCdOhW1tUkBxxHbACNN7g9verwQ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Topaz, C. M., Klingenberg, B., Turek, D., &lt;strong&gt;Heggeseth, B. C.&lt;/strong&gt;, Harris, P. E., Blackwood, J. C., Chavoya, C. O., Nelson, S., and Murphy, K. M. (2019), &amp;ldquo;Diversity of artists in major U.S. museums.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;PLoS ONE&lt;/em&gt;, 14(3): e0212852.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interactive Shiny App: &lt;a href=&#34;https://artofstat.shinyapps.io/ArtistDiversity/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://artofstat.shinyapps.io/ArtistDiversity/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://sinews.siam.org/Details-Page/when-data-meets-diversity?fbclid=IwAR0la1-qIIdKrNdiN-qNSh6DaZnCwfinDZ-kSRhJOxVLCnFiu9DxVnwj3k8&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Heggeseth, B. C.&lt;/strong&gt; and Topaz, C. M. (2020), &amp;ldquo;When Data Meets Diversity.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;SIAMS News&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Diversity on Display at the National Gallery</title>
      <link>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/project/diversityondisplay/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/project/diversityondisplay/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a member of a team of applied mathematicians, statisticians, and art historians and curators, I was invited to participate in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nga.gov/press/2019/datathon.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;National Gallery of Art (NGA) Datathon&lt;/a&gt;. Our task was to analyze, contextualize, and visualize its permanent collection data. Our team focused on the location history of each art object and try to highlight the diversity of art and artists on display at the NGA over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We cleaned, reformatted, and created interactive visualizations on a website that provides access to our explore the diversity spatially and over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The provided data that tells us whether an object is on public view may not accurately reflect actual practice; our data does not include objects that have been in public view in any rooms currently under revonvation. Any objects that were on public view for at least one day of the chosen month were given equal weight in determining these distributions. Artist gender identities were identified from the Union List of Artist Names (provided by the J. Paul Getty Trust), inferred based on the first name using historical data records, or manually determined by an art historian. These identities may not accurately express the artist&amp;rsquo;s self-identity. Artist race/ethnicities identities were inferred using nationalities and group identities listed in the Union List of Artist Names (provided by the J. Paul Getty Trust), and the publicly available National Gallery of Art nationalities, which reflect citizenship. These nationalities and identities were grouped using the U.S. Census Bureau definitions of White, Hispanic, Black, Asian, and Native and they may not accurately express the artist&amp;rsquo;s self-identity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Products&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interactive Shiny App: &lt;a href=&#34;https://bheggeseth.shinyapps.io/DiversityOnDisplay/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://bheggeseth.shinyapps.io/DiversityOnDisplay/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presentation: &lt;strong&gt;Heggeseth, B. C.&lt;/strong&gt;, Topaz, C. M., Nelson, S., Klingenberg, B. (2019), &amp;ldquo;Diversity on Display.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;NGA Datathon&lt;/em&gt;. [&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nga.gov/content/dam/ngaweb/press/2019/datathon/team-4.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PGSNieRw_go&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prenatal Phthalate Exposure and Childhood Growth</title>
      <link>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/project/prenatalphthalate/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/project/prenatalphthalate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In collaboration with epidemiologists at the Center for Environmental Research and Children’s Health in Berkeley, CA, I applied three advanced statistical methods to estimate the association between prenatal exposure of 11 phthalate metabolites and body mass index trajectories. I used generalized additive models, growth mixture models, and functional principal component analysis with regression trees and random forests. The novel contribution in this paper is the additional flexibility in the methods to allow for non-linear relationships between exposures and trajectories and the direct model comparison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Product&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/31102947/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Heggeseth BC&lt;/strong&gt;, Holland N, Eskenazi B, Kogut K, and Harley KG. &amp;ldquo;Heterogeneity in Childhood Growth Trajectories in relation to Prenatal Phthalate Exposure.&amp;rdquo;&amp;quot; &lt;em&gt;Environmental Research&lt;/em&gt;, 175(1): 22-33, 2019.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cricket Courtship</title>
      <link>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/project/crickets/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/project/crickets/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After consulting for a Williams undergraduate student working on a genetics thesis, I became involved in the project to determine the association between the chemical “smell” of crickets and the mating between a pair of crickets. In addition to dealing with the dependence of repeated measures, I used survival analysis techniques to analyze the time until mating commenced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Product&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://bmcecolevol.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12862-020-1587-9&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Heggeseth, B. C.&lt;/strong&gt;, Sim, D., Partida, L., and Maroja, L. (2020) &amp;ldquo;Influence of Female Cuticular Hydrocarbon (CHC) Profile on Male Courtship Behavior in Two Hybridizing Cricket Species Gryllus firmus and Gryllus pennsylvanicus.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;BMC Evolutionary Biology&lt;/em&gt; 20(21). &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Updating Implicit Impressions</title>
      <link>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/project/misattribution/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/project/misattribution/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Mann, Cone, and Ferguson are social psychologists who study explicit and implicit reactions to new information. There have been questions in the scholarly community about whether the main tool that they use to measure implicit reactions, the Affect Misattribution Procedure (AMP), actually measures unintended responses. My contribution to this study was the statistical analysis and interpretation of their analysis. I collaborated with them to analyze repeated measures data from 8 new studies and as well as reanalyze data from their past published studies.  The main statistical concern was whether their previous conclusions were still valid despite the fact the distributions of the observations were bimodal. Thus, I designed a series of analyses that included sensitivity analyses to test the robustness of their conclusions to perturbations in the observed data distribution and pooled analysis across similar experiments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Product&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/30802132/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mann, T. C., Cone, J., &lt;strong&gt;Heggeseth, B. C.&lt;/strong&gt;, and Ferguson, M. J. (2019), &amp;ldquo;Updating implicit impressions: New evidence on intentionality and the Affect Misattribution Procedure.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Journal of Personality and Social Psychology&lt;/em&gt;, 116(3), 349-374.
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prenatal DDT and Childhood Growth</title>
      <link>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/project/prenatalddt/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/project/prenatalddt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This was one of the first applications of growth mixture modeling to environmental epidemiology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deliverable&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0131443&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Heggeseth, B., Harley, K., Warner, M., Jewell, N., &amp;amp; Eskenazi, B. (2015). Detecting associations between early-life DDT exposures and childhood growth patterns: a novel statistical approach. PLoS One, 10(6), e0131443.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parity and BMI in Women</title>
      <link>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/project/paritybmiwomen/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/project/paritybmiwomen/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This work with Dr. Barbara Abrams is an application of GEE models to longitudinal BMI measurements over a woman&amp;rsquo;s lifetime, accounting for the timing and number of births they had in their lifetime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deliverable&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/oby.20503&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Abrams, B., Heggeseth, B., Rehkopf, D., &amp;amp; Davis, E. (2013). Parity and body mass index in US women: a prospective 25‐year study. Obesity, 21(8), 1514-1518.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
