<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Correlated Data | Brianna C. Heggeseth</title>
    <link>bcheggeseth.github.io/tag/correlated-data/</link>
      <atom:link href="bcheggeseth.github.io/tag/correlated-data/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Correlated Data</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2021 Brianna C. Heggeseth </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/bcheggeseth.github.io/media/icon_hu57cb00c344750d07111e480b68a9d566_369349_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Correlated Data</title>
      <link>bcheggeseth.github.io/tag/correlated-data/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prenatal PFAS and Early Childhood Growth</title>
      <link>bcheggeseth.github.io/project/prenatalpfas/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>bcheggeseth.github.io/project/prenatalpfas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2016, Dr. Megan Romano of Dartmouth University contacted me regarding my expertise in longitudinal methods for childhood growth. I helped her write a grant proposal and started working as a statistical consulting on this approved grant that seeks to estimate the relationship between exposure to PFASs and childhood adiposity growth over time. I wrote the analysis plan, implemented it, and we are writing up the conculsions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Product&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In Progress&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prenatal Phthalate Exposure and Childhood Growth</title>
      <link>bcheggeseth.github.io/project/prenatalphthalate/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>bcheggeseth.github.io/project/prenatalphthalate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In collaboration with epidemiologists at the Center for Environmental Research and Children’s Health in Berkeley, CA, I applied three advanced statistical methods to estimate the association between prenatal exposure of 11 phthalate metabolites and body mass index trajectories. I used generalized additive models, growth mixture models, and functional principal component analysis with regression trees and random forests. The novel contribution in this paper is the additional flexibility in the methods to allow for non-linear relationships between exposures and trajectories and the direct model comparison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Product&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/31102947/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Heggeseth BC&lt;/strong&gt;, Holland N, Eskenazi B, Kogut K, and Harley KG. &amp;ldquo;Heterogeneity in Childhood Growth Trajectories in relation to Prenatal Phthalate Exposure.&amp;rdquo;&amp;quot; &lt;em&gt;Environmental Research&lt;/em&gt;, 175(1): 22-33, 2019.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Longitudinal Regression Trees</title>
      <link>bcheggeseth.github.io/project/splinetree/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>bcheggeseth.github.io/project/splinetree/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Work with Anna Neufeld (initially as an Honors project) to review and compare existing methods to create a regression tree based on longitudinal quantitative outcome data and then improving the methodology to be able to detect additive and interactive relationships between baseline covariates and growth patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Product&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://anna-neufeld.github.io/splinetree/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;splinetree&lt;/a&gt; R package is available on CRAN to implement this work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vertically shifted Growth Mixture Models</title>
      <link>bcheggeseth.github.io/project/verticalshifting/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>bcheggeseth.github.io/project/verticalshifting/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Coming out of my dissertation work, I developed a methodological study of mixture models for longitudinal data and their ability to detect growth patterns. In this paper, I showed that the default model assumptions do not necessarily create groups that are homogenous in terms of growth pattern over time as they seek to explain the most variation, whether it be from the overall level or pattern over time. I suggested a pre-processing step that removes the outcome level to explicitly focus on the shape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Product&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://projecteuclid.org/journals/annals-of-applied-statistics/volume-12/issue-1/How-Gaussian-mixture-models-might-miss-detecting-factors-that-impact/10.1214/17-AOAS1066.short&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Heggeseth, B. C.&lt;/strong&gt; and Jewell, N. P. (2018), &amp;ldquo;How Gaussian mixture models might miss detecting factors that impact growth patterns,&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Annals of Applied Statistics&lt;/em&gt;, 12(1): 222-245.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cricket Courtship</title>
      <link>bcheggeseth.github.io/project/crickets/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>bcheggeseth.github.io/project/crickets/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After consulting for a Williams undergraduate student working on a genetics thesis, I became involved in the project to determine the association between the chemical “smell” of crickets and the mating between a pair of crickets. In addition to dealing with the dependence of repeated measures, I used survival analysis techniques to analyze the time until mating commenced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Product&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://bmcecolevol.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12862-020-1587-9&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Heggeseth, B. C.&lt;/strong&gt;, Sim, D., Partida, L., and Maroja, L. (2020) &amp;ldquo;Influence of Female Cuticular Hydrocarbon (CHC) Profile on Male Courtship Behavior in Two Hybridizing Cricket Species Gryllus firmus and Gryllus pennsylvanicus.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;BMC Evolutionary Biology&lt;/em&gt; 20(21). &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
