<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Environmental Epidemiology | Brianna C. Heggeseth</title>
    <link>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/tag/environmental-epidemiology/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://bcheggeseth.github.io/tag/environmental-epidemiology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Environmental Epidemiology</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 Brianna C. Heggeseth </copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/media/icon_hu57cb00c344750d07111e480b68a9d566_369349_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Environmental Epidemiology</title>
      <link>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/tag/environmental-epidemiology/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Associations with Early Kidney Injuries</title>
      <link>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/project/kidneyfunction/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/project/kidneyfunction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2021, my PhD advisor, Nicholas Jewell, put me in contact with &lt;a href=&#34;https://iris.ucl.ac.uk/iris/browse/profile?upi=BCAPL88&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr. Ben Caplin&lt;/a&gt; of University College of London and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.renalfellow.org/2019/02/08/my-journey-from-nicaragua-to-london-to-study-ckdu-5-lessons-learned/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr. Marvin Gonzalez-Quiroz&lt;/a&gt; and their larger &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5210224/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;DEGREE study team&lt;/a&gt; to help them study the potential causes of chronic kidney disease of unexplained cause (CKDu) among young, apparently healthy individuals in Nicaragua.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information about the epidemic of CKDu in Central America, see the &lt;a href=&#34;https://laislanetwork.org/type/video/page/2/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Cycle of Death video&lt;/a&gt; created by the team members and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thelancet.com/pdfs/journals/langlo/PIIS2214-109X%2814%2970217-7.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;a Lancet article&lt;/a&gt; on the topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The research team have been collecting longitudinal data on cohorts of young, healthy people in Nicaragua. After a two-year follow up, they &lt;a href=&#34;https://jasn.asnjournals.org/content/29/8/2200.short&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;applied longitudinal growth mixture models (GMM) to detect any associations with declining eGFR patterns&lt;/a&gt;. While this statistical approach worked well for a short follow up, it was not as applicable for detecting the underlying cause with a longer 5-year follow up since individuals may start to decline at any point during the study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In collaboration with nephrologists, epidemiologists, and statisticians, I came up with an alternative methodology (details forthcoming in publication) to detect an early kidney injury, the time at which an individual might switch from healthy kidney function to declining, unhealthy kidney function before being clinically diagnosed as having CKD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Macalester students, Alexander McCreight and Connie (Yixuan) Zhang, worked with me to implement this method to investigate potential exposures with early kidney injury. The first paper using this method is currently in review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With my students, we will compare the potential conclusions from the original GMM methodology with this alternative method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Product&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In Progress&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prenatal PFAS and Early Childhood Growth</title>
      <link>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/project/prenatalpfas/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/project/prenatalpfas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2016, &lt;a href=&#34;https://geiselmed.dartmouth.edu/epidemiology/people/faculty/megan-romano/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr. Megan Romano&lt;/a&gt; of Dartmouth University contacted me regarding my expertise in longitudinal methods for childhood growth. I helped her write a grant proposal and started working as a statistical consulting on this approved grant that seeks to estimate the relationship between prenatal exposure to PFAS and childhood adiposity growth over time. I wrote the analysis plan, implemented it, and we are writing up the conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Product&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In Progress&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prenatal Phthalate Exposure and Childhood Growth</title>
      <link>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/project/prenatalphthalate/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/project/prenatalphthalate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In collaboration with epidemiologists at the Center for Environmental Research and Children’s Health in Berkeley, CA, I applied three advanced statistical methods to estimate the association between prenatal exposure of 11 phthalate metabolites and body mass index trajectories. I used generalized additive models, growth mixture models, and functional principal component analysis with regression trees and random forests. The novel contribution in this paper is the additional flexibility in the methods to allow for non-linear relationships between exposures and trajectories and the direct model comparison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Product&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/31102947/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Heggeseth BC&lt;/strong&gt;, Holland N, Eskenazi B, Kogut K, and Harley KG. &amp;ldquo;Heterogeneity in Childhood Growth Trajectories in relation to Prenatal Phthalate Exposure.&amp;rdquo;&amp;quot; &lt;em&gt;Environmental Research&lt;/em&gt;, 175(1): 22-33, 2019.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparing Mixture and Mixed Effects Models for baseline exposures and longitudinal growth</title>
      <link>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/project/mixturemixedcomparison/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/project/mixturemixedcomparison/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In summer 2015, I worked with Alvaro Aleman, a Williams student at the time, on comparing two statistical methods for detecting relationships between baseline exposures and longitudinal growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deliverable&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0209321&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Heggeseth, B. C., &amp;amp; Aleman, A. (2018). Early-life environmental exposures and childhood growth: A comparison of statistical methods. PloS one, 13(12), e0209321.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prenatal DDT and Childhood Growth</title>
      <link>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/project/prenatalddt/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bcheggeseth.github.io/project/prenatalddt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This was one of the first applications of growth mixture modeling to environmental epidemiology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deliverable&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0131443&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Heggeseth, B., Harley, K., Warner, M., Jewell, N., &amp;amp; Eskenazi, B. (2015). Detecting associations between early-life DDT exposures and childhood growth patterns: a novel statistical approach. PLoS One, 10(6), e0131443.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
